Finding Aid for John Harvey Kellogg Papers 1832-1965 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Harvey Kellogg Papers [microform] 1832-1965, 1874-1943
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
46 microfilms
Battle Creek, Michigan physician, food scientist, founder of the Battle Creek Sanitarium. Correspondence, student notebooks from University of Michigan and Bellevue Hospital, drafts of speeches and lecture notes, newspaper clippings and scrapbooks, and topical files; include material concerning medical theories and practices, especially matters of diet and hygiene, his work with organizations such as the National Vitality League, Race Betterment Foundation, Battle Creek Three Quarter Century Club, Chicago Workingmen's Home and Medical Mission, and Seventh-Day Adventists; also photographs.
89500 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Gertrude W. Goodwin (Donor No. 3506 ), secretary of the Race Betterment Foundation of Battle Creek, Michigan.
The collection is open for research.
The originals of this collection are available for use at the Bentley Historical Library. The microfilm can be borrowed through inter-library loan.
John Harvey Kellogg, born February 26, 1852, earned worldwide acclaim in his lifetime as a health reformer and propagandist, and as head of the Battle Creek Sanitarium. Kellogg is now best known in connection with the line of breakfast cereal products made by the company that bears his name. While John Harvey Kellogg conceived the notion of flaked corn as a healthful morning repast, it was his brother, Will Keith, who turned his hand to the development of the breakfast food company. John Harvey Kellogg was also a skilled surgeon, an editor, and scientist who saw himself as primarily an educator determined to focus public attention on preventive medicine as the means to maintain good health. The main thrust of Kellogg's good health message was that vegetarian diet, regular exercise, fresh air, and sunshine are the keys to a long and vigorous life. Kellogg was a testament to the efficacy of his principles, living to age ninety-one and working diligently until succumbing to pneumonia on December 14, 1943.
Kellogg's father, a convert to Seventh Day Adventism, moved his family to Battle Creek when John Harvey was age four; thus the young Kellogg grew up well versed in the health reform principles of the Adventists. Many of these tenets, especially regarding vegetarianism and temperance, were elements of Kellogg's mature thinking on healthful "biologic living." Kellogg, an 1875 graduate of Bellevue Hospital Medical College, brought a solid training in orthodox medicine to his health reform efforts. In this, he differed from most earlier health reformers, whose systems often lacked grounding in science. Kellogg made repeated trips to Europe to keep abreast of developments in medicine, surgery, and physiology in order to buttress the scientific foundations which supported his health teachings.
Upon completion of his medical training, Kellogg returned as medical superintendent of the Adventists' Western Health Reform Institute in Battle Creek. Kellogg's vigorous efforts as a promoter and publicist soon brought the Battle Creek Sanitarium (as the Institute was renamed in 1876) to national prominence as "a place where people learn to stay well." Kellogg used the Sanitarium as a testing ground for the application of his "Battle Creek idea" on the effect of diet, exercise, correct posture, fresh air, and rest on the health and fitness of individuals. The program did enhance health. Kellogg and the Sanitarium prospered, despite policy differences with the Seventh Day Adventists, a 1902 fire which destroyed the building, and receivership debt due to overbuilding, until the 1930s Depression cut down patronage. In good times, Kellogg traded heavily on the celebrity of the Sanitarium's clientele to sell his health reform ideas. In hard times, he relied on the strength of the science which girded his system to keep pushing health. Throughout his sixty-seven year association with the Sanitarium, Kellogg never wavered in his faith in the rectitude of the "Battle Creek idea."
Kellogg was a prolific author and had a ready venue of publication in Good Health, a magazine he edited for nearly seventy years. Kellogg incorporated many of the ideas which appeared first as articles in Good Health into nearly fifty books. Included among them are: Body in Health, Colon Hygiene, New Dietetics, Plain Facts about Sexual Life, Practical Manual of Health and Temperance, and Rational Hydrotherapy. These books manifest Kellogg's efforts to bring the new medical science to the general public. Kellogg also lectured from coast-to-coast touring his message before as large an audience as possible. Finally, Kellogg's dynamic personality attracted disciples to Battle Creek to study at the feet of the master of "rational" medicine; these disciples in turn propagated Kellogg's ideas that medical science pointed to adherence to a vegetarian regimen of moderation as the surest way to good health.
The John Harvey Kellogg papers document the career of a medical doctor and health reformer and advocate. The collection provides telling insight to the operation of the Battle Creek Sanitarium. The papers span the years 1869 to 1965, with the bulk of the materials covering the years 1874 to 1943. Significantly, there are some collected published items in the collection that date as early as 1832. The Kellogg papers consist of correspondence, lectures, notes, memoranda, clippings, scrapbooks, notebooks, photographs, articles, and book manuscripts. These diverse sources provide ample documentation of Kellogg's life, and are an excellent source with which to examine early twentieth-century medicine in general and Kellogg's important innovations in health reform. The collection is also very strong on the development of the Sanitarium and the "Battle Creek idea " of natural health. Kellogg's zealous efforts to proselytize the world at large on the wisdom of the "Battle Creek Idea" are reflected in the papers. Also included are materials relating to his work with organizations such as the National Vitality League, Race Betterment Foundation, Battle Creek Three Quarter Century Club, Chicago Workingmen's Home and Medical Mission, and Seventh-Day Adventists.
The Kellogg collection came to the Michigan Historical Collections in two primary accessions, one in 1962 and another in 1972. Parts of the collection were reprocessed in 1988 prior to the entire collection being microfilmed. The collection is now divided into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Lectures, Speeches, and Related; Notes and Articles; Subject Files; Clippings/ Scrapbooks; Bound Manuscripts/Published Volumes; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Battle Creek (Mich.); Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Bellevue Hospital.; Chicago Workingmen's Home and Medical Mission.; Depressions--1929--United States.; Food.; Hygiene.; Ireland.; Medicine--Michigan--Battle Creek.; National Vitality League.; Physicians--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Prohibition--United States.; Public health--United States.; Race Betterment Foundation.; Physicians--Religious life--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Seventh Day Adventist Church (Battle Creek, Mich.); Three Quarter Century Club (Battle Creek, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Battle Creek (Mich.)--Buildings.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Health resorts.; Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Buildings--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Buildings--Illinois--Chicago.; Chicago (Ill.)--Buildings.; Chicago (Ill.)--Missions.; Dwellings--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Families.; Health resorts--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Hospitals--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Interiors.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Kellogg family.; Laboratories.; Medicine--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Missions--Illinois--Chicago.; Physical fitness.; Slums.; Women.
Contributors:
Barron, Clarence Walker, 1855-1928.; Boldyreff, W.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.; Campbell, B. Hodges.; Edison, Mary Stilwell.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.; Efromoff, G.; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947.; Ford, Clara Bryant, 1866-1950.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; LeHand, Margaret.; Liebold, Ernest G., 1884-; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Parran, Thomas.; Pavlov, Ivan Petrovich, 1849-1936.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Plunckett, Horace.; Pomari, M.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Tarbell, Ida M. (Ida Minerva), 1857-1944.; Tissier, L.; Tolstoy, Alexandra, 1884-1979.; Tolstoy, Ilga.; Tolstoy, Leo, 1828-1910.; Van Shaick, Louis J.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal/biographical
  Biographical/Personal (0.1 lin. ft.) is a small series drawn from different parts of the collection containing summary information about Kellogg's life as well as some of the awards he received throughout his career.
  - Autobiographical and Biographical Notes (Reel 1)
  - Awards, citations, etc. (Reel 1)
    (also oversized items filmed on reel 46)
- Correspondence 1875-1948, 2 linear feet
  The Correspondence series (2 linear ft.; 1875-1948) documents Kellogg's many interests and the operation of the sanitarium. Correspondents in the collection include C. W. Barron, Richard E. Byrd, Mary G. Edison, Irving Fisher, Clara J. Ford, Henry Ford, Margaret LeHand, Ernest G. Liebold, Chase S. Osborn, I. P. Pavlov, Gifford Pinchot, Hazen Pingree, Sir Horace Plunckett, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Franklin D. Roosevelt, Bernard Shaw, William Howard Taft, Ida Tarbell, Alexandra Tolstoi, Leo Tolstoi, Ilga Tolstoi, and Louis J. Van Shaick.
  - 1875-1918 (Reel 1)
  - 1919-1925 (Reel 2)
  - 1926-1935 (Reel 3)
  - 1935-February 15, 1938 (Reel 4)
  - February 16, 1938-1941 (Reel 5)
  - 1942-1948 (Reel 6)
- Lectures, speeches, and related 1875-1943, 4.5 linear feet
  The researcher will find the fullest development of Kellogg's thinking on any specific topic in the Lectures, Speeches, and Related series (4.5 lin. ft.; 1875-1943). This series is arranged chronologically.
  - 1875-October 1898 (Reel 6)
  - October, 1898-May 1901 (Reel 7)
  - June 1901-August, 1903 (Reel 8)
  - September 1903-December, 1905 (Reel 9)
  - January 1906-July, 1908 (Reel 10)
  - August 1908-September, 1910 (Reel 11)
  - October 1910-July, 1911 (Reel 12)
  - August 1911-March, 1913 (Reel 13)
  - April 1913-July, 1914 (Reel 14)
  - August, 1914-1922 (Reel 15)
  - 1923-1933 (Reel 16)
  - 1934-1943 (Reel 17)
- Notes and Articles (by topic) circa 1890-1943, 4 linear feet
  The Notes and Articles (by topic) series (4 linear ft.; ca. 1890-ca. 1943) contains miscellaneous original and collected material, not always clearly identified. It is arranged alphabetically by broad topic.
  - Alcohol (Reel 17)
  - Arthritis (Reel 17)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium (Reel 17)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium (Reel 18)
  - Biologic Living (Reel 18)
  - Catalog of Kellogg Library (Reel 18)
  - Circulatory System (Reel 18)
  - Colon and Gastro-Intestinal Tract (Reel 18)
  - Diet for special age groups and special cases (Reel 18)
  - Diet--General (Reel 18)
  - Diet--General (Reel 19)
  - Dietetics (Reel 19)
  - Diseases and Diagnoses (Reel 19)
  - Diseases and Diagnoses (Reel 20)
  - Dress (Reel 20)
  - Education (Reel 20)
  - Electric current for medical use (Reel 20)
  - Exercise (Reel 20)
  - Exercise (Reel 21)
  - Food (Reel 21)
  - Health (Reel 22)
  - History and Health (Reel 22)
  - Hydrotherapy (Reel 22)
  - Hydrotherapy (Reel 23)
  - Longevity (Reel 23)
  - Manual Swedish Movements (Reel 23)
  - Meats, tobacco, tea, and coffee (Reel 23)
  - "Natural Living" (Reel 23)
  - Physiology (Reel 23)
  - Physiology (Reel 24)
  - Politics (Reel 24)
  - Question Box Lectures (Reel 24)
  - Race Betterment/Eugenics (Reel 24)
  - Thermotherapy-Miscellaneous (Reel 25)
  - Women's Work/Housekeeping (Reel 25)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 25)
- Notes and Memoranda (dated) 1876-1941, 1.5 linear feet
  - 1876-1906 (Reel 25)
  - 1907-1941 (Reel 26)
  - 1942-1943 (Reel 27)
- Subject Files circa 1885-1920, 1.3 linear feet
  Subject Files (1.3 lin. ft. ca. 1885-1920) is arranged alphabetically by topic and relates primarily to Kellogg's interest in medical missionaries.
  - American Medical Missionary College (Reel 27)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium (Reel 28)
  - Chicago Medical Missionary School (Reel 28)
  - Chicago Medical Missions (Reel 28)
  - Christian Help Bands (Reel 28)
  - International Health Association (Reel 28)
  - International Medical Alliance (Reel 28)
  - International Medical Missionary and Benevolent Association (Reel 28)
  - International Medical Missionary Conference (Reel 29)
  - Legal Papers and Patents (Reel 29)
  - Medical Faculty Meetings (Reel 29)
  - Medical Missionary
    - Board (Reel 29)
    - Convention/Conference (Reel 29)
    - General (Reel 29)
    - Lectures (Reel 30)
    - Miscellaneous and Fragments (Reel 30)
    - Published (Reel 30)
  - Mexican Medical Missions (Reel 30)
  - Michigan Sanitarium and Benevolent Association (Reel 30)
  - Sanitarium Training School for Missionary Nurses (Reel 30)
  - Sanitariums (various states) (Reel 30)
  - Seventh Day Adventist Medical Missionary and Benevolent Association (Reel 30)
  - Soul (Nature of) (Reel 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 31)
- Clippings/Scrapbooks 1878-1952, 2 linear feet
  The Clippings/Scrapbooks (2 lin. ft.; 1878-1952) consists of clipping files arranged both chronologically and by topic, and scrapbooks arranged chronologically supplemented by volumes pertaining to specific topics.
  - Clippings (dated) 1879-1952 (Reel 32)
  - Clippings (undated) circa 1890-1965
    - Arthritis (Reel 32)
    - Battle Creek College (Reel 32)
    - Battle Creek Sanitarium (Reel 33)
    - Biologic Living (Reel 33)
    - Health Training (Reel 33)
    - Kellogg, John Harvey (Reel 34)
      - Biographical (Reel 34)
      - Theory and Writings (Reel 34)
    - Longevity (Reel 34)
    - Medical Missionaries (Reel 34)
    - Race Betterment (Reel 35)
    - Three Quarter Century Club (Reel 35)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 35)
  - Scrapbooks (unbound) 1878-1929 (Reel 35)
  - Scrapbooks 1904-1924 (Reel 35)
  - Scrapbooks 1925-1944 (Reel 36)
  - Scrapbooks 1904-1944 (Reel 46)
    (oversize volume filmed with other outsize materials on reel 46)
  - Scrapbooks (undated) circa 1900-1940 (Reel 36)
- Bound Manuscripts/Published Volumes circa 1869-1940, 4.5 linear feet
  Bound Manuscripts/Published Volumes (4.5 lin. ft.; ca. 1869-ca. 1940) consists of various ledgers and daybooks, Kellogg's student notebooks, his professional notebooks, manuscripts of essays and other writings, and published works by Kellogg and others in the field of health and nutrition. The notebooks in particular manifests Kellogg's quick mind as student and as a doctor in search of the most recent trends in medicine and surgery. Not part of this Kellogg collection, but also available at the Bentley Historical Library, is a collection of Kellogg's published writings and the Good Health magazine.
  - Guestbooks and Registers (Reel 36)
  - Miscellaneous bound materials (primarily family materials) (Reel 37)
  - Ledgers and Daybooks 1889-1923 (Reel 37)
  - Index Rerum circa 1888-1896 (Reel 37)
  - Notebooks
    - Student 1869-1873 (Reel 37)
    - Student 1874-1875 (Reel 38)
    - Professional 1876-1899 (Reel 38)
    - Professional 1899-1927 (Reel 39)
  - Printed works by Kellogg and Sanitarium doctors circa 1890-1940
    - Diseases, diagnosis and treatment (Reel 40)
    - Food and dietetics (Reel 40)
    - General (Reel 40)
    - Health and Medical Institutions (Reel 40)
    - Iron Ration (Reel 40)
  - Bound Manuscripts by Kellogg circa 1890-1925
    - Health Compendium (Reel 41)
    - Man the Masterpiece (Reel 41)
    - Nature's Remedies (Reel 41)
    - Miscellaneous fragments (Reel 41)
  - Works by Others (manuscripts) circa 1885-1940
    - A-L (Reel 42)
    - M-Z (Reel 43)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 44)
  - Van Noorden's Metabolism and Practical Medicine (Reel 44)
  - Works by Others (printed) circa 1832-1940
    - Alcohol (Reel 44)
    - Colon and Gastro-Intestinal Tract (Reel 44)
    - Diet and Food (Reel 44)
    - Disease, Diagnosis and Treatment (Reel 44)
    - General Health (Reel 44)
    - Race Betterment/Eugenics (Reel 44)
- Photographs, circa 1880-1940s, 0.8 linear feet
  The Photograph series (0.8 lin. ft.; ca. 1880s-ca. 1940s) includes portraits and photos of John Harvey Kellogg with family and friends, other photos concerning the Battle Creek Sanitarium, its buildings and the activities that it administered, Kellogg's interest in a Chicago mission house, and Kellogg's travels. There are also family photos.
  - Portraits (Reel 45)
  - Informal photos of John Harvey Kellogg (alone) (Reel 45)
  - Informal photos of John Harvey Kellogg (with others) (Reel 45)
  - Christmas card photographs (Reel 45)
  - Interiors and exteriors of Battle Creek home (Reel 45)
    (also oversized photographs filmed on reel 46)
  - Kellogg (Mrs.) John Harvey (Reel 45)
  - Kellogg family (Reel 45)
  - Travels
    - Africa 1925-1926 (Reel 45)
    - California 1928 (Reel 45)
    - Florida 1918-1919, 1929-1930 (Reel 45)
    - Leysin, Switzerland (Dr. Rollier's clinic) (Reel 45)
  - Chicago Mission (Reel 45)
  - Chicago Slums (Reel 45)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium (old) (Reel 45)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium (new)
    - Dedication ceremonies (Reel 45)
    - Buildings (Reel 45)
    - Interiors (Reel 45)
    - Laboratory scenes, 2 folders (Reel 45)
    - Pavlov Physiological Institute (Reel 45)
    - Physical fitness program, 2 folders (Reel 45)
    - Deer Park (Reel 45)
    - Other activities (Reel 45)
    - Staff (Reel 45)
  - American Medical Missionary College (Reel 45)
  - Portraits and miscellaneous (non-John Harvey Kellogg) (Reel 45)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Reel 45)
  - Album re: summer playground-nutrition program for children 1926 (Reel 46)
    (oversized volume filmed with outsized items on reel 46)